DHIMAN TALAPATRA

Full Stack Engineer







Full Stack Engineer with Cloud Development experience. 13+ years of industry experience in delivering solutions for the Banking and Telecom Domain across multiple technologies including CI/CD, UX, Cloud Technologies. AWS Developer Associate, CSM Scrum Master certified, having experience in managing and collaborating with various teams to deliver onlime solutions.







dhiman.talapatra@gmail.com tttps://dhimantalapatra.com in https://www.linkedin.com/in/dhiman-talapatra

WORK EXPERIENCE

Jul 2018 - Present Cognizant Technology solutions **Senior Associate**

Current Role and Responsibilities:

Solution Architect / Scrum Master

- Responsible for providing High and Low level design of software components. Based on microservices architecture using cloud technologies. Ensuring scalability, performance and security aspects are followed as per industry standard.
- Ensure all agile methodology and ceremonies are followed in a sprint.
- Get involved in ideation processes with Business stakeholders at customer location.

Past Roles

Offshore lead

- Responsible for delivery of green field projects.
- Responsible for Maintenance and enhancements of multiple applications.

Dec 2014 - Jun 2018 Cognizant Technology solutions **Associate**

Roles and Responsibilities

Team lead

- Responsible for end to end delivery of 5 member team.
- Coach junior members for upskilling.

Full Stack Developer

- Implement individual modules across back and front end.
- Create Wire Frames for GUI upgrade and Angular migration.
- Work on Migration projects like. CORBA to SOAP Web Service.

Jul 2014 - Dec 2014 HCL Technologies Limited **Lead Engineer**

Roles and Responsibilities

Team lead

- Responsible for delivery of enhancements / bug fixes for 3 member team. Full stack Java Developer
 - Develop enhancements and bug fixes across application layers.

Oct 2012 - Jun 2014 HCL Technologies Limited **Software Engineer**

SKILLS

Cloud

AWS, OpenShift, Heroku, Firebase

DevOps

Jenkins, Git-Lab CI/CD, Heroku Pipeline

Containerization

Docker, Kubernetes

Java

Core Java, Spring, JSF

Front-End

Angular, React, Bootstrap CSS

Mobile

Flutter, Android, PWA

Other Languages

Kotlin, Python, Unix Shell Script

EDUCATION

2005 - 2009

Graduation - B.TECH - Electronics & Instrumentation Guru Nanak Institute of Technology, Sodepur

2003 - 2005

Roles and Responsibilities

Full stack Java Developer

Develop enhancements and bug fixes across application layers.

Selenium automation developer

• Maintain an automation test suite for an existing enterprise application.

Feb 2011 - Oct 2012 Infosys Limited

Senior Systems Engineer

Roles and Responsibilities

Java Developer

- Work on Change Requests for Finacle Banking solution.
- Work on bug fixes for product stabilization.

Feb 2010 - Jan 2011 Infosys Limited

Systems Engineer

Roles and Responsibilities

Junior Java developer

• Work on bug fixes for product stabilization.

Senior Secondary - Science 10+2 ST Xavier's Institution, Panihati

2002 - 2002

Secondary 10

Douglas Memorial High School, Barrackpore

CERTIFICATIONS

Nov 2022 Azure Certification (Cognizant Internal)

Design an application that involved very common functionalities, like Authentication and authorization, event based and API based communication between micro services utilizing Azure basics. Lambda, VMs, Kubernetes, API gateway, Queues etc

Nov 2020 AWS Certified Developer - Associate (DVA)

Amazon Simple Queue Service, Amazon DynamoDB, Amazon ElastiCache, Amazon Kinesis, AWS Lambda, Amazon API Gateway, AWS Elastic Beanstalk, AWS Identity and Access Management, AWS Key Management Service.

Jun 2019 CSM Certified Scrum Master

Agile Methodology, Roles and responsibilities of scrum master ,Various SCRUM parameters and measures, SCRUM ceremonies.

Mar 2019 Knowledge Stalwarts

Recognition of excellence in training and consistent high feedback from training participants.

Oct 2018 Full Stack Engineer

Angular (Angular material), Docker, Spring Boot (Secure REST PI with token based authentication), MySQL

Jul 2014 Hadoop and BIG data

concepts of Hadoop Distributed File System and MapReduce, Setup a Hadoop Cluster, Understand Data Loading Techniques using Sqoop and Flume, Perform Data Analytics using Pig and Hive, Work on a Real Life Project on Big Data Analytics and gain Hands on Project Experience

PERSONAL INFO

Present Address Talackerstrasse 49, Glattbrugg 8152, Zurich, Switzerland

Permanent Address 43/B Rabindrapally Netaji Road, Barrackpore, Kolkata-700122.

Languages Known

Bengali, English, Hindi

Blood Group A+

Passport Number P4264937 Date of Birth 30th April 1987 Marital Status Married

I hereby declare that the above mentioned facts are true to the best of my knowledge.